













    
        
    

    

    

    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/cto-diaries/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
            
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/cto-diaries/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/cto-diaries/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        
            <copyright>© Flowerinthenight, 2016-2024. All rights reserved.</copyright>
        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2023-08-09 00:00:00 -0700 PDT</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/cto-diaries/</link>

        
            <managingEditor>example@example.com (John Doe)</managingEditor>
        

        <title>Cto-Diaries · Tags · About</title>

        
            <webMaster>example@example.com (John Doe)</webMaster>
        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Hi. It’s been a year since my last「CTO diaries」post. Never mind the excuses, there’s a lot.</p>
<p>Anyway, so what does my typical, or normal day, look like? Well, I usually start the day with checking the overall health of our systems. We don’t really have very sophisticated monitoring and alerting systems at this point so this means checking on several areas such as our Kubernetes clusters, databases, and critical services. On top of my head, I think the most common service crashes I noticed so far are OOM-related.</p>
<p>I also check our month-to-date infrastructure spending. We use bits of the three (AWS, GCP, and Azure). I don’t really do this meticulously; more like checking for anomalies. We’ve been hacked several times in the past for mining and these usually show up as cost anomalies. I can also keep an eye on unpredictable usages such as data transfers. Our runway is one of the many things in my list of concerns so I’d like to keep an eye on runaway costs as much as I can.</p>
<p>A huge chunk of the day is spent doing admin tasks. In our current phase, I’m actually more of an engineering manager than a CTO. I take part in daily standups, backlog grooming, dealing with developer blockers, schedules and priorities, interfacing with technical support, product, and customer success teams. While these are fairly straightforward, I would say that the additional overhead of “context-switching” between Japanese and English is surprisingly high, at least for me. The constant worry of whether I was able to communicate what I wanted to communicate, and all the nuances that come with that, is always there. Writing on top of verbal communication always helps.</p>
<p>Then 1-on-1’s. It’s not daily but it takes a huge amount of my time and energy. It’s not really that bad overall but it’s probably the most exhausting, personally. Dealing with people, with different personalities, is always a challenge, both at work and outside. I’m not a people-person really; my EQ leaves a lot to be desired. But I like to think that I’m getting good at it though.</p>
<p>Another part of my typical day is reading. Anything that I deem beneficial really; technical articles and papers, new developments in technology that are related to our domain, applied psychology — interestingly, business and startups, the lot. I would say this is probably the part I enjoy the most.</p>
<p>Last is coding, which I usually do during the wee hours of the night. Not core codebase though, mind, but support code such as tooling, CI/CD, and scaling. This is probably out of necessity more than anything. I don’t really enjoy coding that much anymore, even before I became CTO but we still can’t afford domain experts at the moment so I contribute as much as I can.</p>
<p>I’ll probably write about the other bits like participating in investor meetings, sync-ups with other executives, etc. on a separate post.</p>
<p>Alright, that&rsquo;s it. See you in the next one.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,0001-01-01:/blog/2022-09-27-cto-diaries-typical-day/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/2022-09-27-cto-diaries-typical-day/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>CTO Diaries #2: Typical day</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>So far, I&rsquo;ve been posting some techy stuff here and there but being a CTO of a relatively small, Japan-based startup for about three years now, I thought I&rsquo;d share some of my experiences along the way. But first off, a little bit of context: the company I work for, <a href="https://alphaus.cloud/">Alphaus Cloud</a> is fairly small; about 10 engineers scattered across three countries, although at one point, we hit at around 35. It started around 2015, did three product pivots, three rounds of funding under two CEOs. At the moment, we operate within the Cloud FinOps (financial operations) segment of the market. As for myself, I am what you would consider an &lsquo;accidental CTO&rsquo;, a term I came across from <a href="https://cto.academy/diary-of-an-accidental-cto-part-1/">CTO Academy</a>, and a term I quite like: i.e. &ldquo;someone who arrived in the CTO role ahead of schedule and is grappling with new challenges and very steep learning curve&rdquo;. You can call it luck, although that would be relative, depending on one&rsquo;s interpretation. Also, Japanese is not my native tongue, although I think I can hold my own in day-to-day conversations, nor is English, but I think I&rsquo;m fairly proficient at it. And even though the company is trying to expand its operations outside of Japan, it is still inherently Japanese as far as business operations are concerned: the CEO/COO, sales, customer success teams are Japanese, investors are Japanese, and majority of our clients are also Japanese companies.</p>
<p>The CTO role in such a setup is quite unclear. Even though I had some experience leading tech teams in the past, nothing could have prepared me for this role. For one, my blunders are now more costly. My decisions now affect multiple teams, not just the engineering team. I have to undestand the business side of the company. I need to understand company financials. My &lsquo;soft skills&rsquo; now matter more than ever; people, relationships, empathy, politics, the lot: they&rsquo;re probably more difficult, and exhausting, than the technology part of my role. With that said though, overall, I&rsquo;m enjoying it so far. There&rsquo;s a certain charm to it that I can&rsquo;t really explain; I thought I wouldn&rsquo;t like it at first, me being an introvert and all, but the challenges are instructional and character-building enough that I welcome, sort of, the stress associated with it.</p>
<p>My goal in this series is to share some of my experiences from this side of the world in the hopes that it will help others gain some perspective. Mind you, this is the internet, and these are just my opinions, take them with a pinch of salt. And finally, I&rsquo;m still not sure how to make this series more accessible from the blog. The &rsquo;tags&rsquo; section is probably the faster way to search for it for now. Maybe I&rsquo;ll provide a dedicated page in the future, who knows, we&rsquo;ll see.</p>
<p>Alright, that&rsquo;s it. See you in the next one.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,0001-01-01:/blog/2021-09-28-cto-diaries-intro/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/2021-09-28-cto-diaries-intro/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>CTO Diaries #1: Introduction</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
